Welcome back, fellow Rustaceans!
欢迎回来，Rust 开发者们！
In the previous module on variables,
在上一讲“变量”中，
we said that every variable
提到每个 Rust 的变量
in Rust has a type. You've likely used
都有类型。或许你已经
types similar to Rust's in other
在其他语言中接触过和 Rust 类似的类型了，
languages such as C, Ruby,
这些语言有 C，Ruby，
or Java.
Java。
In this module, we're going to go through
在这一讲，我们将会讲到
the basic types provided by the core language
由语言核心提供的基本类型，
to get you familiar with how to use them
这会让你更加熟悉在 Rust 中如何使用他们。
in Rust. In a future module,
在之后的章节里，
we'll talk about custom types that you can define
我们还会讲到可以由你设计的自定义类型。
Let's start with Booleans.
让我们从 Booleans 开始吧。
Booleans are called "bool"
Booleans 在 Rust 中的类型名是“bool”。
in Rust. A Boolean
1个 Boolean 型变量
can be either true
的值可以是 true
or false. Booleans are often used
或者 false。Booleans 常常用在
in conditional control flow statements
条件判断中，
like if and while.
例如 if 语句和 while 语句。
Here, we have two Boolean variables.
看这儿的两个 Boolean 型变量，
Variable a is set to true,
变量 a 被赋值 true，
and variable b is set to false.
变量 b 被赋值 false。
The first if statement
头一个 if 语句
tests a,
判断 a，
and the second tests
第二个 if 语句判断 b。
b. Because only a is
由于只有 a 是 true，
true, this code will only execute
这个代码将只会执行
the first block, printing a is
第一个花括号的代码块，并输出"a is true!"。
Now, let's turn to integers.
接下来，我们转向学习整型。
Numbers without decimal points are called
在 Rust 里，没有小数点的数字
integers in Rust.
就是整型数字。
There are two types of integers: signed
整型还分两种：有符号
and unsigned.
和无符号。
Additionally, you have to decide
进一步地，你还需要确定
how much space your integers will use,
你要用的整数要占用多少空间，
which affects the values that the integer can hold.
这会影响整数变量能存储多大的整数。
This allows your program to use only
这种精打细算的思考会让你的程序恰好
the amount of memory it needs
只使用够用的内存，
and no more.
不会浪费空间。
The number in each type indicates
每种类型中的数字代表
how many bits it takes to store a value
在程序中它要占多少比特的空间。
For example, an
例如，
i8 takes up 8 bits.
一个 i8 型变量占用8比特空间。
Because i means signed,
由于 i 代表有符号的意思，
one of those bits is used to store
最高位的比特位用来表示
whether the number is positive
这个数字是正数还是负数。
The rest of the bits store the value of
其余比特位才是存储该变量的值。
This means that an i8 can store
这意味着一个 i8 型变量能
the values between -128
存储的值的范围是-128
and 127, inclusive.
到127。
If the number you want to store can only
如果你要存的数字
be 0 or positive,
只可能是0或这正数，
you can use an unsigned type
你可以使用一个无符号类型变量
instead.
来代替。
An unsigned type uses the letter
无符号类型使用字母 u
u instead of i.
代替 i。
Because the unsigned types don't
由于无符号类型不使用
use a bit to store the sign,
额外的1比特位来存储符号，
the range of values they can store is different.
该类型变量能存储的值的范围有所不同。
A u8 can store the values
一个 u8 型变量存储的值的范围
between 0
是0到
and 255, inclusive.
255。
The isize and usize integer types
isize 和 usize 类型能存储的值的范围和
are architecture dependent.
硬件相关。
If you're on a 32-bit machine,
如果跑在 32位机器上，
they will take up 32 bits of space.
isize 和 usize要占用 32比特的空间。
But if you're on a 64-bit machine,
但如果运行在 64位机器上，那
they will take up 64 bits.
它们就会占用 64比特空间。
This is the size of a pointer on each
与此类似，指针占用空间的大小也和上述类型一样，
of these architectures.
和机器类型相关。
You use isize
可以使用 isize
and usize for indexing into collections
或 usize 来索引集合
or counting items.
或用来计数。
In this code,
如图所示代码，
a ﻿is an array of integers
a 是包含整形数字的数组，
and the 0 used to index into the array
用来索引的数字0
has the type usize.
是 usize 类型。
We're going to talk more about arrays in a minute.
我们稍后再讲一下数组。
Without any other information,
默认情况下，
if you write a number without a decimal point in
在 Rust 中写了一个不带小数点的数字，
Rust, its type will be i32
那它的类型就是 i32.
This is a decent default if you're not sure
如果你不确定要用哪种整数类型，
which integer type to use.
那 i32 就是个不错的默认选项。
Next, let's talk about floating-point numbers.
接下来，聊聊浮点数。
Numbers with a decimal point are called
带有小数点的数字称为
floating-point numbers.
浮点数。
Like integers, they come in different sizes:
就像整数一样，浮点数也有不同尺寸的类型：
f32
f32
and f64using 32
和 f64，
and 64 bits, respectively.
分别使用 32bit 和 64bit 空间。
The default type of a floating-point number
浮点数的默认类型是
is f64, which
f64，
offers more precision than an f32.
这比 f32 提供了更高的精度。
Operating on floating-point numbers
在计算机中操作浮点数
in computers can be complicated.
可能是个复杂问题。
If you've never had to deal
如果你从来没处理过
with them before,
浮点数问题，
please see The Floating-Point Guide.
请阅读《The Floating-Point Guide》（https://floating-point-gui.de/ 译者按）
Characters are our last simple
字符类型是简单类型中的最后
data type.
一种。
Rust can store single characters
Rust 可以将单个字符
as the chardata type.
作为 char 类型存储。
char is a Unicode scalar value,
char 是一个 Unicoce scalar value（术语，参看 https://zhuanlan.zhihu.com/p/53714077 理解，译者按）
so it can hold more than just ASCII values.
所以它能保存的不仅仅是 ASCII 值。
Because languages are complicated,
由于人类的语言是复杂的，
a char might not correspond to what
Rust 里的 char 可能不符合
we humans expect a character to be.
我们人类所期望的字符的样子。
Characters are written
字符被单引号
with single quotes.
包裹的。
Don't confuse them with strings, which use double
不要把它们和双引号包裹的字符串混淆。
quotes.
quotes.
Booleans, integers, floating-point
布尔类型，整数类型，浮点数类型，
numbers, and characters are the simple
和字符类型是刚刚讲的
built-in types we're going to talk about.
内置的简单类型。
Next come the compound built-in types,
接下来是内置的复合类型，
starting with tuples.
先从元组开始。
Tuples let you group multiple values
元组允许你将多个值
together within parentheses.
用括号组合在一起。
These multiple values don't have to be
这些多个值不必是
the same type.
相同类型。
Here, ﻿tup is a tuple
看这个例子，tup变量是
with three elements:
一个有3个元素的tuple（后面类型术语就不翻译了，译者按）：
an i32,
一个 i32，
a char,
一个 char，
and a bool.
和一个 bool。
To get individual items out of a tuple,
为了从tuple里获取单个元素，
we use tuple indexing.
可以使用tuple索引。
Tuple indexing uses a dot followed
tuple索引用点号跟着
by the index of the item you want, starting
你想要获取的元素的索引来表达，索引
from 0.
从0开始。
This code prints the first is
这段代码打印“the first is
1 and
1”，和
the second is c.
“the second is c”。
To break the entire tuple into separate pieces,
要将tuple拆成多个值，
you can use destructuring.
可使用解构语法。
To do so, match the structure
要做到这一点，在等号左边
of your tuple on the left-hand side
使用符合tuple结构的
of a let statement before the equals
let语句。
This statement will put 1 in x,
这个语句让x等于1，
the character c in y,
y等于'c'，
and the Boolean true in z.
z等于布尔值 true。
Let's discuss arrays
接下来我们聊聊
next.
数组。
Arrays in Rust are collections where
rust中的数组是一个集合，
all of the elements have the same type.
其中所有元素都有相同的类型。
This is an array of three
这里有个包含3个 f64 类型元素
f64 values.
的数组。
You can access each element of an array
你可以通过使用方括号
by using square brackets
和索引值
and the index of the element you want,
来访问数组中的每个元素，
starting from 0.
索引值从0开始。
This code will print out the second element of
这段代码将会输出数组的第2个元素，
the array, 3.14.
3.14。
You can also modify an element of an
还可以用方括号语法
array using square brackets.
来修改某个位置的元素。
This code will print out the array
这段代码将把数组的
with the first element set to 0.
第一个元素设置为0，并打引出来。
We can see this when we run the code, which
运行这段代码，
prints out the array after changing it.
可以看到值确实改变了。
Arrays have a fixed length set
数组在初始化完成后
when you initialize them. They can't
长度是固定的。不能再变得
get bigger or smaller. Even though
更大或更小。尽管
the array b is mutable,
数组b是可变的，
we can't add another element to it to
但我们不能向其再增加元素，
make it four elements long instead of three.
使它变成4个元素而不是3个。
If we try to add another element to the array,
如果尝试向数组添加元素，
the compiler says we're not allowed.
编译器不会允许这样做。
If you need a sequence of values that can change
如果需要一个可变的集合，
in size, you can use a Vec –
可以使用Vec，
a type provided by the standard library.
Vec是标准库提供的类型。
One primitive type you will see a lot
另一种很常见的原始类型是
is called a slice.
slice。
Slices let us reference a contiguous
slice可以引用另一个数据中
subset of data in another data
一个连续的数据子集。
structure.
structure.
The type of variable ﻿b here would
变量b的类型读作
be read as a slice of i32s.
元素类型为i32的slice。
Here, b refers to the elements
这个例子中，b指向a中
of a for the indices 0,
的索引0（包括）到
inclusive, to 1, exclusive,
索引1（不包括）的部分，
which, in this case, would only
具体来说就是
be the element 100.
元素100。
A specific kind of slice is the string
一种特殊的切片是字符串切片，
slice written as &amp;
写做“&str”。
String literals are a common way
通过使用字符串字面量，是一种常见的
to create string slices.
创建字符串切片的方式。
We'll talk about string slices in more depth
我们讲将在下一章更深入地
in the next unit along
探讨字符串切片和
with regular slices.
普通的切片。
In this module,
在本节中，
we've shown you that Rust has a wide assortment
我们介绍了Rust中各种各样的
of primitive data types.
原始数据类型。
In future modules,
在之后的课程里，
we'll talk about combining primitive data types
我们还要介绍使用结构体和
to build complex data types using structs
枚举来构建复杂类型。